<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag: Icon | 乐者为王]]></title>
  <link href="http://codemany.com/tags/icon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://codemany.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-09T11:18:09+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://codemany.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[dohkoos]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[如何创建有效的图标]]></title>
    <link href="http://codemany.com/blog/how-to-create-effective-icons/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-06T12:43:17+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://codemany.com/blog/how-to-create-effective-icons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>英文原文：<a href="http://www.awwwards.com/how-to-create-effective-icons.html">http://www.awwwards.com/how-to-create-effective-icons.html</a></p>

<p>我可能就是你所说的图标爱好者。我喜欢图标，而且我更加喜欢制作它们！作为一个艺术家，我的背景在很大程度上是绘画——我喜欢绘画，并且我已经画了一辈子（甚至远远早于我知道什么是图形设计）。我想，这是我理解创建图标的一个关键。绘画教你看——然后把你所看到的转化成纸上的线条和图形——而这正是如何创建有效的图标。</p>

<h3 id="几何图形">几何图形</h3>

<p>因此，对初学者而言，基本上任何东西都可以用这四种图形组合而成：</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-1.png" title="effective-icons-1" ></p>

<p>当我想把某事物转换成一个图标时，我观察它然后尽可能地将其拆分为最简单的图形。例如，水滴可以用一个三角形和一个圆形组成。</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-2.png" title="effective-icons-2" ></p>

<p>心形图标可以由两个圆形和一个三角形构成。</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-3.png" title="effective-icons-3" ></p>

<p>我每次都是在Adobe Illustrator中创建这些图形。使用矢量图形可以让我控制线条的粗细，以及图形和其锚点的相互作用。Illustrator也可以让我自由地把线条转换成图形，反之亦然。这一切也许看起来十分基础，但它是我用于创建最复杂图标的同样的方法。下面是我最近在做的一个略微更加复杂些的《权利法案》图标的示例，在这里我应用了同样的原则。</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-4.png" title="effective-icons-4" ></p>

<h3 id="界面图标">界面图标</h3>

<p>I recently got to do a set of icons for an awesome iPhone app called the Parker Planner. I really enjoyed working on this project, and one of the most important aspects of the project was to create an understandable, ownable, functional, and beautiful set of user interface icons that would help users navigate this semi-complicated planning application.</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-5.png" title="effective-icons-5" ></p>

<p>Let’s take one of these icons and break it down to see how I created it. The trash can icon, for example, is composed of three rounded rectangles and three lines.</p>

<ol>
<li>Choose the Rounded rectangle tool</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-6.png" title="effective-icons-6" ></p>

<ol>
<li>Drag out a shape</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-7.png" title="effective-icons-7" ></p>

<ol>
<li>Play with the stroke weight until you’re satisfied.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-8.png" title="effective-icons-8" ></p>

<p>I usually choose one or two stroke weights to use throughout a set of icons.</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-9.png" title="effective-icons-9" ></p>

<p>This helps them look more consistent and feel more cohesive.</p>

<ol>
<li>Create the lid with another rounded rectangle.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-10.png" title="effective-icons-10" ></p>

<ol>
<li>One more rounded rectangle creates the handle of the lid.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-11.png" title="effective-icons-11" ></p>

<ol>
<li>Erase the bottom half of your rounded rectangle.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-12.png" title="effective-icons-12" ></p>

<ol>
<li>Now add the stripes on the can by adding three vertical lines to the can’s body.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-13.png" title="effective-icons-13" ></p>

<ol>
<li>And there you have it! A trash can icon... if you like, you can play around further with color or line weights</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-14.png" title="effective-icons-14" ></p>

<p>A few other really helpful tools I use often when creating icons are the pathfinder, which I use to cut, join, and knock out shapes;</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-15.png" title="effective-icons-15" ></p>

<p>The Stroke/Fill tool, which helps you toggle shapes from fill to stroke.</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-16.png" title="effective-icons-16" ></p>

<p>And my very favorite tool, the Stroke Panel, which helps you transform corners and line terminals from straight to rounded.</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-17.png" title="effective-icons-17" ></p>

<p>When I am finished with a set of icons, I usually line them all up next to each other to see if any of them look weird or out of place. Then I make any necessary changes.</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-18.png" title="effective-icons-18" ></p>

<p>Lastly, I always test them in-app to make sure that they feel right and function well.</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/effective-icons-19.png" title="effective-icons-19" ></p>

<p>In the end, I would say that the way to create great icons is more than just learning illustrator tricks, although that is necessary as well. The best thing to do, is to practice breaking things you see around you into simple shapes. And the better you get at that, the more masterful iconographer you can become! Cheers. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
